<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:webfeeds="http://webfeeds.org/rss/1.0">

 <title>I'm Lovin' I.T. - Julien Sobczak</title>
 <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/"/>
 <updated>2024-05-03T09:08:18+00:00</updated>
 <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Julien Sobczak</name>
 </author>

 <webfeeds:cover image="https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/cover.png" />
 <webfeeds:icon>https://www.juliensobczak.com/android-chrome-192x192.png</webfeeds:icon>
 <webfeeds:logo>https://www.juliensobczak.com/favicon-32x32.png</webfeeds:logo>
 <webfeeds:accentColor>4185f4</webfeeds:accentColor>
 <webfeeds:related layout="card" target="browser"/>

 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: The Checklist Manifesto: How to Get Things Right</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/07/17/the-checklist-manifesto.html"/>
   <updated>2023-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/07/17/the-checklist-manifesto</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       Effective teamwork using the cheapest technique
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/the-checklist-manifesto.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: The Checklist Manifesto: How to Get Things Right&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;Simple techniques can produce huge results. But more often than not, simple techniques are easy to explain but hard to put into practice efficiently. A checklist is definitely one of these techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book follows the reflection of a surgeon on using checklists like aviation pilots use them. The book follows how the idea grew inside the author’s mind, which means the pace of the book is sometimes slow. For sure, you can easily sum up the book in a few pages but getting into details contributes a lot in appreciating the subtleties of using a checklist that really works in practice. (The number of complications after surgery dropped nearly by half everywhere such a “simple” technique was applied!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a surgeon, the author focuses on using checklists in the operation room but the reflection will help you apply the knowledge in other domains where teamwork and preventing errors is essential. As brilliantly illustrated through real-world use cases, checklists are cheap but surprisingly effective. Checklists will make your team more efficient without necessarily being more skillful.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: Reinventing Organizations: An Illustrated Invitation to Join the Conversation on Next-Stage Organizations</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/07/06/reinventing-organizations-illustrated.html"/>
   <updated>2023-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/07/06/reinventing-organizations-illustrated</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       A peek into the right way to work
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/reinventing-organizations-illustrated.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: Reinventing Organizations: An Illustrated Invitation to Join the Conversation on Next-Stage Organizations&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reinventing Organizations&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most cited management books. The original version is 300-page long, not so long for an eye-opening book, but probably too long as few people read, especially management books. This new illustrated edition introduces the same ideas and is half the size (including the numerous well-designed illustrations) so that you can read it almost in one sitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lessons behind these books emerge from the author’s research across mostly 12 organizations. I love how the author chose “normal” companies, not the famous success stories where it’s too easy to find reasons why results cannot be replicated. In fact, these “normal” companies are even more impressive. All around the world, people dare to act differently. When you stop seeing organizations as machines that must be optimized but as living systems that are constantly growing, you enter a world of new possibilities. A world where the way to work is more natural, but feels sadly not natural, at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way we worked at the beginning of our career will not be the way we will work when we will retire. Things must change. Things will change. This book has already demonstrated its potential to ignite change. We need more experiences like the ones described in this book. We are at an interesting point in work history. There is so much more to be written on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: The Culture Code: The Secrets of Highly Successful Groups</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/07/04/the-culture-code.html"/>
   <updated>2023-07-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/07/04/the-culture-code</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       An interesting perspective on group culture based on real-world examples.
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/the-culture-code.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: The Culture Code: The Secrets of Highly Successful Groups&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;Group culture is one of the most powerful forces on the planet. If you want to go fast, go alone, if you want to go far, go together (African Proverb). Companies know the impact of having a strong culture but we just don’t know how it works. Culture is kind of mysterious. The common solution for companies is to document values that describe who they want to be and rarely who they really are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the recipe of the excellent &lt;em&gt;The Talent Code&lt;/em&gt;, Daniel Coyle spend four years visiting eight successful groups, including a special-ops military unit, a professional basketball team, a movie studio, a comedy troupe, and a gang of jewel thieves. This book decodes the key ingredients behind these successful cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book consists of three parts focusing on these three ingredients — build safety, share vulnerability, and establish purpose. Each chapter presents one or two stories. It means there are relatively few examples, but each story is presented with enough details to grasp the subtleties of each context. Each part ends with concrete suggestions to experiment in your own context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, successful cultures are still hard to define. There is no easy path toward a culture that works. The book is probably the most comprehensive study and the best resource to find ideas for actions.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: The Talent Code: Greatness Isn&apos;t Born. It&apos;s Grown. Here&apos;s How</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/06/29/the-talent-code.html"/>
   <updated>2023-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/06/29/the-talent-code</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       A passionate journey in the world of skill acquisition
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/the-talent-code.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: The Talent Code: Greatness Isn&apos;t Born. It&apos;s Grown. Here&apos;s How&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;The book follows the author in the most surprising talent hotbeds like a tennis court in Moscow, a soccer field in São Paolo, a vocal studio in Dallas, or a baseball-mad island in the Caribbean. We learn about the “secrets” behind the top performers like the best soccer players, bank robbers, violinists, or fighter pilots. We meet scientists, coaches, and teachers that are explaining their discoveries concerning the acquisition of skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;Peak&lt;/em&gt; by Anders Ericson is the best book to learn about the path to expertise, &lt;em&gt;The Talent Code&lt;/em&gt; is the best supplement to understand the role of deep practice (aka deliberate practice) from a low-level viewpoint. You will learn about myelin, the substance that wraps the neural circuits you trigger through practice and that increases signal strength, speed, and accuracy. The more you practice, the more myelin you build. Myelin is for sure promising and represents the core argument of this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read a lot about learning. It’s one of the best books on the subject of excellence. It can replace advantageously an often-cited book, &lt;em&gt;Outliers&lt;/em&gt;, which fails short in comparison.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: Time Off: A Practical Guide to Building Your Rest Ethic and Finding Success Without the Stress</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/06/02/time-off.html"/>
   <updated>2023-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/06/02/time-off</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       When rest is not the inverse of work
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/time-off.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: Time Off: A Practical Guide to Building Your Rest Ethic and Finding Success Without the Stress&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;The last decades of busyness work cannot be considered quality work. The greatest minds in history understood the need for time off. Using history as the best evidence, you will learn from Aristotle, Beethoven, and also from famous innovators, Nobel Prize winners, prolific artists and so much more. You will understand why time off will help you live a happier, fulfilled life, and at the same time, make you more productive and creative than you have ever been. You cannot be successful in the long-term feeling overwhelmed. Success requires time off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I love about this book is that the focus is on being more creative, not simply on slowing down. This book will make you enjoy time off without feeling guilty. Using the latest research about creativity, sleep, play and a wealth of inspiring stories, &lt;em&gt;Time Off&lt;/em&gt; will help you develop a better work ethic AND a rest ethic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predictions are hard, especially about the future of the workplace. Working long hours will probably not be as “effective” when IA will be omnipresent. The book makes a great argument about embracing time off to stay relevant. The future of the workplace must integrate our potential of creative human beings that desperately need time off for that.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: Tribe of Mentors: Short Life Advice from the Best in the World</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/05/25/tribe-of-mentors.html"/>
   <updated>2023-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/05/25/tribe-of-mentors</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       Invaluable wisdom hidden between the lines
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/tribe-of-mentors.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: Tribe of Mentors: Short Life Advice from the Best in the World&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;If you loved &lt;em&gt;Tools of Titans&lt;/em&gt;, you will love even more &lt;em&gt;Tribe of Mentors&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this new book, Tim emailed his mentors the same well-thought questions and half of them take hours or days to write sophisticated answers (about success, happiness, focus, meditation, Stoicm, sports, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find once again more than 100 chapters from a diverse panel of contributors (still mostly American). Unlike &lt;em&gt;Tools of Titans&lt;/em&gt; where the notes were edited by Tim Ferris, the answers in this book were written by their authors. There is no organization in this book, “just” a collection of wisdoms, to read and reread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If learning from your own experience seems a good idea, this book will make it obvious that learning from others’ experiences is even more invaluable and indispensable.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: Limitless: Upgrade Your Brain, Learn Anything Faster, and Unlock Your Exceptional Life</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/05/15/limitless.html"/>
   <updated>2023-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/05/15/limitless</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       Learning the growth mindset by example.
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/limitless.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: Limitless: Upgrade Your Brain, Learn Anything Faster, and Unlock Your Exceptional Life&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;Jim Kwik suffered from a head injury when he was a small kid that impaired his focus, concentration, and ability to learn. The “boy with the broken brain” has now become one of the main experts on learning and one of the best examples of human potential, coaching along the way so many celebrities over three decades (just have a look at the long list of praises at the beginning of the book).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I love about this book is its powerful message. Jim Kwik is a formidable storyteller to challenge all your misconceptions about learning. Don’t let a limit in your mindset, motivation, or methods stop you to learn. If you need to be challenged about your ability to learn, you have found the book you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love how the story of the author perfectly illustrates the magic of books. If books can change us, this one is a great testimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What could have been better is the presentation of techniques. The principles behind techniques are not clearly articulated to apply them successfully and techniques are introduced without showing their importance. For example, designing effective flashcards or writing useful notes are key techniques that have a larger impact than some other techniques but that are particularly challenging to put into practice. The book &lt;em&gt;A Mind for Numbers&lt;/em&gt; is more practical and preferable if you are interested in techniques. But both books are incomplete. There is always more to learn but once you know you can learn anything, nothing seems impossible.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: Tools of Titans: The Tactics, Routines, and Habits of Billionaires, Icons, and World-Class Performers</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/04/18/tools-of-titans.html"/>
   <updated>2023-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/04/18/tools-of-titans</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       A treasure book
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/tools-of-titans.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: Tools of Titans: The Tactics, Routines, and Habits of Billionaires, Icons, and World-Class Performers&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;Tim Ferris delivered once again a book like no other one. He spend a month reviewing the notes taken during the interviews of his podcasts (and a few more months editing them). The result is a collection of “tools,” including routines, books, common self-talk, supplements, favorite questions, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book organization is minimal (to say the least). Three parts (Healthy, Wealthy, and Wise) where wealthy means much more than money and extends to abundance in time, relationships, and so much more. Tim Ferris assigned each personality to one of these parts but subjects are constantly overlapping as all parts are required for a meaningful and happy life. The lack of structure may seem disturbing as you have to process, digest, and organize the information yourself, but the effort is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The personalities are diverse (authors, athletes, doctors, artists, politicians, etc.) which makes this book even more valuable (but as they are mostly all living in the American culture, the diversity could have been even better). There are so many things to experiment with. If you try them all at once, it would be a disaster. All successful contributors to this book use a few key techniques or processes that make a huge difference for them. You need to find the ones to adapt, to try first, to delay and to ignore. It’s the kind of book where you can find something new every time you open it. It’s the kind of book you cannot ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check also &lt;em&gt;Tribe of Mentors&lt;/em&gt;, by the same author, which I found even more inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: Make Time: How to Focus on What Matters Every Day</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/03/31/make-time.html"/>
   <updated>2023-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/03/31/make-time</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       Time Management in a time-deprived world.
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/make-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: Make Time: How to Focus on What Matters Every Day&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Make Time&lt;/em&gt; is like a cookbook. “You wouldn’t try all the recipes at once,” say the authors, “and you don’t need to do all the tactics at once, either.” It’s a book to find what best works for YOU based on a list of more than 80 tactics to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors spent years at Google as product designers, helping to build services like Gmail, YouTube, and Google Hangouts (= helping to steal our attention). Their reflection on this experience makes this book particularly valuable as they decided to use their unique perspective to design the most invaluable product: how we spend our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors declare &lt;em&gt;Make Time&lt;/em&gt; is not about productivity but all great productivity books focus on the same goal as this book: create more time in your day for the things you care about. I found the book pleasant, and engaging, especially if you are tired of how ineffective you are at work and are ready to make some practical changes in your habits. It’s clearly not a definitive book on the subject. Other books like &lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/em&gt; are more inspiring but less practical but it’s a great choice as a first reading on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;


   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>Book Review: Understanding Software Dynamics</title>
   <link href="https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/03/28/understanding-software-dynamics.html"/>
   <updated>2023-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://www.juliensobczak.com/read/2023/03/28/understanding-software-dynamics</id>
   
   <content type="html">
   	 &lt;img class=&quot;webfeedsFeaturedVisual&quot; alt=&quot;Article Image&quot; src=&quot;https://www.juliensobczak.com/img/post-read-lite.png&quot;&gt;
     
     &lt;p&gt;
       Lessons learned after 55 years spent living at the intersection of hardware and software.
     &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;cover&quot; src=&quot;/posts_resources/covers/understanding-software-dynamics.png&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover - Book Review: Understanding Software Dynamics&quot; /&gt;
    
     &lt;p&gt;Software has rarely demonstrated the same gain of performance as hardware. Understanding the performance of complex software is difficult. “Without a good picture of reality, programmers are reduced to guessing and &lt;em&gt;trying things&lt;/em&gt; to reduce long delays and improve performance,” declares the author. “This book is about not guessing, but knowing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author has worked with giants such as Frances Allen, Fred Brooks, John Cocke, and Don Knuth and has co-designed the DEC industry, worked on Adobe Photoshop and improved the performance of Google services like Gmail. It’s one of these rare books that result from a unique experience of more than five decades at the intersection of hardware and software. For sure one of the most important programming books published in the last decade. For a limited audience…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will learn what happens when you run instructions on a CPU that read and write from memory, disks or the network, from the lowest viewpoint, and most importantly, how to reason when facing a problem affecting the long tail latency (= the few abnormal slow requests) using common commands, logging, profiling, and tracing. Examples are written in C or C++ and running on Linux. Not all code examples are included in the text and must be downloaded, which sometimes makes comprehension difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is a great complement to &lt;em&gt;Systems Performance&lt;/em&gt; by Brendan Gregg. It’s (maybe) less practical but (maybe) more timeless as more focused on principles than the tools at hand. A great book for curious developers and an indispensable resource for performance engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

   </content>
   
 </entry>
 
 

</feed>